NYSUT Boards of Directors Meetings. 6174/015
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Boards of Directors Meetings
1938-1981
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/015
5 cubic feet
5 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, publications, minutes.
The series spans the late 1960s to 1981, with a few documents dating from the 1950s and as early as 1938, but focuses mainly on the early 1970s, the formative years of NYSUT as it emerged from NYSTA (New York State Teachers Association) and struggled with the question of unity with the National Education Association (NEA) versus affiliation with the AFL-CIO and the American Federation of Teachers. Issues of professionalism -- respect, recognition, and individual autonomy -- clashed with the practical desire for higher wages and benefits that was seen to be achievable only through following the industrial model of traditional labor organization. That tension was perfectly articulated in a speech by NYSTA's executive secretary Francis White to the House of Delegates shortly before his resignation, when he warned that the union could not achieve the militancy and effectiveness of the Teamsters without the unity and discipline of the Teamsters. In the end, the Board of Directors chose the industrial path, rejecting the elitist pretentions of the NEA, whose sense of exclusivity extended even to barring full membership by non-teaching school employees. For years to come, NYSUT and the NEA would exist as competing organizations in New York State, but the political acumen developed out of the conflict by the NYSUT elected officers would serve the union well in its dealings with the State Education Department, legislature, and local school boards. The collection includes testimony by officers before the state legislature, records of committees studying educational issues such as mainstreaming developmentally disabled students, and internal issues such as awards criteria, as well as the files of the annual conventions (House of Delegates/Representative Assembly). Both NEA and NYSTA/NYSUT board meetings are represented.
6923061
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 25, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
The series spans the late 1960s to 1981, with a few documents dating from the 1950s and as early as 1938, but focuses mainly on the early 1970s, the formative years of NYSUT as it emerged from NYSTA (New York State Teachers Association) and struggled with the question of unity with the National Education Association (NEA) versus affiliation with the AFL-CIO and the American Federation of Teachers. Issues of professionalism -- respect, recognition, and individual autonomy -- clashed with the practical desire for higher wages and benefits that was seen to be achievable only through following the industrial model of traditional labor organization. That tension was perfectly articulated in a speech by NYSTA's executive secretary Francis White to the House of Delegates shortly before his resignation, when he warned that the union could not achieve the militancy and effectiveness of the Teamsters without the unity and discipline of the Teamsters. In the end, the Board of Directors chose the industrial path, rejecting the elitist pretentions of the NEA, whose sense of exclusivity extended even to barring full membership by non-teaching school employees. For years to come, NYSUT and the NEA would exist as competing organizations in New York State, but the political acumen developed out of the conflict by the NYSUT elected officers would serve the union well in its dealings with the State Education Department, legislature, and local school boards.
Scope and Contents
The series spans the late 1960s to 1981, with a few documents dating from the 1950s and as early as 1938, but focuses mainly on the early 1970s, the formative years of NYSUT as it emerged from NYSTA (New York State Teachers Association) and struggled with the question of unity with the National Education Association (NEA) versus affiliation with the AFL-CIO and the American Federation of Teachers. Records of the boards of directors of all three organizations (NEA, NYSTA, and NYSUT) are included. Also included are records of the interim New York Congress of Teachers, records of committees dealing with issues ranging from redistricting to retirement, testimony of officers to the state legislature, and convention materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); Teachers' union, New York (State). Constitutions.; Teachers' union, New York (State). Handbooks, manuals, etc.; White, Francis; New York State United Teachers. Archives
6923061
- House of Delegates, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) Delegate Handbook, 1971, 1972; Special House of Delegates Handbook, 1972; Special House of Delegates List of Delegates, 1972; List of Delegates on file as of April 7, 1972; NYSTA Constitution and Bylaws, as amended though November 1971; President's Report, 1972 (Thomas Y. Hobart); 1970 Handbook for Delegates; 1969 Handbook for Delegates; materials for credentials and registration for Special House of Delegates, June 17, 1972
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  6/72. National Education Association Board of Directors Agenda, June 21-23, 1972; list of NEA Board of Directors, revised December 1971; list of current assignments of NEA Board of Directors as of November 30, 1971; report of Executive Secretary Sam M. Lambert, June 27, 1972
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  4/72. Minutes; agenda; actions of the NEA Board of Directors, April 28-30, 1972; report to the NEA Board of Directors by Committee on Planning and Organizational Development, "NEA Relationships with National Power Groups" (i.e., AFT/ALF-CIO)
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  10/22-24/71. Minutes; agenda; excerpts from report to Board of Directors October 22, 1971, Sam M. Lambert, Executive Secretary; action items
- NEA-Executive Committee Meeting, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  4/3/71-4/73. Official minutes
- NEA-Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes and Agenda, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  4/71-5/73. Official minutes
- Executive Secretary (NYSTA), 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Brochures introducing Francis J. White, Jr., as new executive secretary of New York State Teachers Association; Memorandum of Agreement with White; summary of unofficial meeting of the joint NYSTA/UTNY Boards of Directors, August 27, 1972; Comprehensive Report and Recommendations to the Board of Directors of the Recruitment Committee, March 14, 1970; Announcement for the position of executive secretary of the New York State Teachers Association; correspondence from candidate, withdrawing from consideration; agreement between the New York State Teachers Association and the NYSTA Employees Organization, 1969-1971; related correspondence; handwritten notes
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  June. Agenda
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  July. Minutes of the Board of Directors, May 4-6, 1973; memos to Board of Directors from NEA president Catharine Barrett and executive secretary Terry Herndon re teacher unity/merger issues and UniServ, June 1973; confidential Opinion Report to NEA Officers and Staff re survey of NEA members, December 1972; proposed NEA constitution; Preliminary Report to the NEA Board of Directors by the NEA Committee on Program and Budget: Technical Book (Revised), June 15, 1975; NEA Special Services Committee (Economic Services) Report to the Board of Directors, 1972-73, June 29, 1973; Charter, Bylaws, and Rules of the National Education Association of he United States of America, July 1972; Resolution and Other Actions, July 1972; Proposed Amendments to the Bylaws and Standing Rules, 1973; NEA Representative Assembly Task Forces and Committees of the Board of Directors and Executive Committee, 1973 membership list; International Teachers' Organizations and Their Conflicts; chart, International Teacher Organizations of Worldwide Importance
- NEA-Board Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Feb. Agenda; Minutes of the Board of Directors, February 4-6, 1972; actions of the NEA Board of Directors; Task Forces and Subcommittees Booklet, December 1971
- NEA Convention, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Alphabetical delegate listing; agenda; rules; committee proposals; delegate proposals; roll call
- Press Releases and Hearings (NYSTA), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  New York State Teachers Association press releases; statements by NYSTA president Emanuel Kafka and executive secretary G. Howard Goold at legislative hearings
- Executive Secretary Reports, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  NYSTA 1971 Annual Report; 1970 New York State Teachers' Association Annual Report of the Executive Secretary; 1969 Annual Report of the Executive Secretary; annual reports,1968, 1967, 1966, 1964, 1962-1963, 1961-1962
- Insurance Reports, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Report of Study of Dental Health Insurance Plans by the Health Insurance Committee of the New York State Teachers Association, submitted to the House of Delegates November 24-27, 1963; Exhibits on Non-Profit Group Dental Insurance Plans
- Info for Speeches, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Handwritten drafts of speech; brochure, Charter Affiliation: Questions and Answers on a New and Important Program; fact sheets; press releases
- Speeches, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Statements by NYSTA president Emanuel Kafka before legislative committees
- Speeches, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Statement by NYSTA president Emanuel Kafka to Temporary State Commission on Campus Unrest; statement to the Board of Regents
- Remarks-Speeches-Articles, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Advisories and press releases by NYSTA warning teachers not to apply for employment at Comsewogue School District (Port Jefferson Station) because of lack of cooperation by administration with teachers' union, 1970; statements by NYSTA president Emanuel Kafka and executive secretary G. Howard Goold to legislative committees, 1969; confidential memo to the professional autonomy task force, May 1969; annual report of task force to NYSTA Board of Directors, August 1969; handwritten notes/drafts of speeches; document, "State Support for Public Schools: The Current Picture: A Kit for Lay Speakers and Committees," February 1970
- Remarks, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Article and cover letter re performance contracting; NYSTA Legislative Bulletin, April 1971; text of Senate and Assembly bills; State Education Department document, "A New Style of Certification"; memo from Emanuel Kafka to NYSTA Board of Directors re action plan to fight the "Jerabek Bills," April 7, 1971; summary of bills and list of voting record by legislators; confidential memo summarizing meeting with Gov. Rockefeller re legislation, March 19, 1971; memo re campaign for additional state aid for schools, April 26, 1971; text of Jerebek bills in Assembly, March 2, 1971; NYSTA Legislative Bulletins, 1971; announcement by NEA of formation of coalition of public employee organizations with AFSME, April 1971; statement from NYSTA, condemning coalition
- President's Page, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Typed notes for column; drafts of article; correspondence and resolution re tenure law
- Background on E. Kafka-Resume, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Letter to Kafka from Gov. Nelson Rockefeller, summarizing support for teachers by his administration, October 15, 1970; NYSTA press releases, announcing endorsements of state and congressional races, condemning Wappingers Falls Board of Education, 1970; bio of Kafka, 1970; letters of congratulations to Kafka on his election to NYSTA board of directors, second vice president, 1964-67; letter advising Kafka that he had been nominated for first vice president, 1968; acceptance letter from Kafka; drafts of speeches; annual report of the president, Emanuel Kafka, to NYSTA House of Delegates, November 7, 1971; annual report of the executive secretary, Dr. Francis White, to the House of Delegates, November 7, 1971; flyer for Kafka for first vice president; New York State Education magazine, with list of nominees for officers, November 1966
- NYCT Ad. Com. and Exec. Com. Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Minutes of New York Congress of Teachers/New York State United Teachers Executive Committee and Joint AdCom (Administrative) /Executive Committee; New York Congress of Teachers Interim Governance Structure directory 1972-73
- NEA Rep Assembly, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  New York State Delegation Business Meetings, NEA Convention, Portland, Oregon, June 29-July 6, 1973; newspaper clippings; NEA Program Budget, fiscal year 1973-74, preliminary report; Report on the Resolutions of the National Education Association, 111th annual meeting, July 5-6, 1973; Fact Sheet on the Decriminalization of Marihuana; campaign booklet for Antonia Cortese for NEA vice president/president elect and Walter Tice, NEA Executive Committee; NYSUT Hotline National Convention Notes, May 6, 1973
- House of Delegates, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Full Text of Resolutions Adopted by the 1968 House of Delegates; New York State Teachers Association List of Delegates, November 24-26, 1968; Code of Ethics of the Education Profession, adopted by the NEA Representative Assembly, July 1968; agenda for delegate assembly; proposed 1969 legislative program; handbook for delegates; New York State Teachers Association Report of the Resolutions Committee, House of Delegates
- NYSUT Rep Assembly, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  NYSUT Representative Assembly List of Representatives, March 23-25, Montreal, Canada; Resolutions presented to the First Annual Representative Assembly of New York State United Teachers (New York Congress of Teachers); Representative Handbook; related materials
- House of Delegates, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Handbook for Delegates, 1967 and 1968 House of Delegates, New York State Teachers Association
- NYSUT Exec. Board of Directors, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  New York State Teachers Association and United Teachers of New York combined personnel list, fiscal year September 1, 1972-August 31, 1973; United Teachers of New York State Report, Year Ended August 31, 1972; proposed constitution, New York Congress of Teachers; agendas, IGS Joint Board of Directors/Executive Council, 1972; membership reports; expense reports; Status of Outstanding Cases in Legal Department as of September 20, 1972; NYSTA staff list; procedure for transmittal of dues and membership information, September 26, 1972; annual report of NYSTA Human Relations Council; Progress Report of NYSTA Certification Task Force, August 1972; Judicial Committee year-end report, July 21, 1972; related documents
- House of Delegates, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Rosters of delegates
- House of Delegates Spec., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Computer printouts of delegates; rosters of visitors
- House of Delegates, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Printed lists
- Official List of Delegates, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Printed lists by election district
- Official List of Delegates, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Official List of Delegates, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Official List of Delegates, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Official List of Delegates, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Official List of Delegates, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Official List of Delegates, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Official List of Delegates, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Official List of Delegates, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Official List of Delegates, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Official List of Delegates, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Official List of Delegates, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Typed lists
- Official List of Delegates, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Official List of Delegates, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Official List of Delegates, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Official List of Delegates, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Official List of Delegates, 1938-1946 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Professional Standards Committee, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  List of members and contact information
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  List of committees; list of commissions, committees, councils, and task forces
- NYSTA Credentials Committee Files, 1965-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Minutes of Credentials Committee in preparation for the House of Delegates, June 16, 1972; correspondence challenging the election of delegates by the Rochester Teachers Association; letters expressing concern re election procedure for delegates from other districts
- NYSTA Committee Files, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Reports of committees and task forces
- Credentials Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  List of members; meeting notifications; minutes
- EEO Through Human Dignity and Instructional Improvement Advisory Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Description of committee and list of members; letter from Lois Wilson to NYSTA Board of Directors re seminars for teachers who have been identified as effective in integrated classrooms, July 14, 1972
- Election Procedures Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Description of committee and list of members
- Finance Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Higher Education Representation Task Force Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Description of committee and list of members; report of the task force
- Human Relations Council, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Description of committee and list of members; annual report
- Judicial Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Description of committee and list of members; year-end report
- Legislative Communications Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Mary Muldoon Teacher Assistance Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Nominations Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Recruitment Committee for Executive Secy., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Excerpt of minutes from Executive Session, establishing committee
- Resolutions Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- NYSTA Teacher Rights Fund Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Retirement Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Unification Task Force Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Description of committee and list of members; meeting notices; minutes; report to the Board of Directors
- VOTE State Steering Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Description of committee and list of members; brochures describing VOTE (Voice of Teachers for Education)
- NYSTA Welfare Fund Trust Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Committee on Teacher Centers, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Headquarters registration form; description of committee and list of members
- Board of Directors, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  List of officers and members of Board of Directors of NYSTA, 1971 and 1972; list of at-large representatives to 1973 NYSUT Representative Assembly; list of UTNY Executive Council and officers, 10/06/72; letter to NYSTA Board of Directors re 1971 Pre-House of Delegates Election District meetings
- Memos and Pending Committee Personnel, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  NYSUT and New York Congress of Teachers Interim Governance Structure directories, 1972-73; description of function and list of members of Credentials Committee; NYSTA newsletter, Guidelines for Local Leaders, October 7, 1971
- Alternate Board of Directors, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  List of alternate Board of Directors; excerpts of minutes
- NYSTA Certification Task Force Committee, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Election Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  List of members; list of members of Convention Committee, Credentials Committee, Elections Committee, Tellers, Sergeants-at-Arms, and Convention Resolutions Committee Chairmen
- Political Action Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Information and Training Manual for VOTE/COPE 1974 Campaign; constitution of VOTE- The Committee on Political Education; recommendation to the president of NYSUT that VOTE and COPE should be merged, May 4, 1973; Committee on Political Action proposed guidelines for political endorsements for NYSUT; related materials
- Committee on Committees, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Committee on Committees report, recommending committees for 1974-76; resolution establishing Committee on Committees and appointing members
- Board of Directors NYSUT Inc., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Ballot for NEA director candidates; 1973-74 directory, Board of Directors; areas of geographic responsibility of Executive Committee members; lists
- NYSUT Memos and Pending, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  List of committees; blank headquarters registration forms for committees; sample letters to nominated members of committees
- Committee to Study Class Size, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Progress report, November 2, 1973; preliminary report, May 10, 1974; list of members
- Convention Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  List of members; report and recommendations; campaign and election procedures
- Credentials Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Lists of members
- Review Committee on Guidelines for Legal Services, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  Resolutions establishing committee
- Planning, Programming, Budgeting, EVA. Systems, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  Resolution establishing committee
- Implementation of Rep. Assembly Resolutions, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  Resolutions establishing committees